A Guide to the Abraham Pais papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA014
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Manuscripts, 1875-2000; 2; 8.5 Cubic Feet
  - "Inward Bound", 1897-1988; 4
    - Manuscript - Master Copy - A History of Elementary Particles [Original Version of "Inward Bound"], undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Master Copy - A History of Elementary Particles [Original Version of "Inward Bound"], undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 3 - From Uranic Rays to Radioactivity, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 4 - The First Particle, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 5 - Earliest Physiological Discoveries, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 6 - Radioactivity's Three Early Puzzles, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 7 - Pitfalls of Simplicity, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 8 - beta-Spectra, 1907-1914, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 9 - Atomic Structure and Spectral Lines, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 10 - 'It was the epoch of belier, it was the epoch of incredulity', undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 11 - Nuclear Physics' Tender Age, undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 11 - Nuclear Physics' Tender Age, undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 11 - Nuclear Physics' Tender Age, undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 12 - Quantum Mechanics, An Essay, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 13 - First Encounters with Symmetry and Invariance, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 14 - Nuclear Physics, the Age of Paradox, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 15 - Quantum Fields, or How Particles are Made and How They Disappear, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 16 - Battling the Infinite, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 17 - In Which the Nucleus Acquires a New Constituent, Loses an Old One, Reveals New Forces with New Symmetries, and is Explored by New Experimental Methods, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 18 - Of Quantum Electrodynamics' Triumphs and Limitations and of a New Particle's Sobering Impact, undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 19 - In Which Particle Physics Enters the Era of Big Machines and Big Detectors and Pion Physics Goes Through Ups and Downs, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 19 - In Which Particle Physics Enters the Era of Big Machines and Big Detectors and Pion Physics Goes Through Ups and Downs, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 20 - Onset of An Era: New Forms of Matter Appear, Old Symmetries Crumble, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 20 - Onset of An Era: New Forms of Matter Appear, Old Symmetries Crumble, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 21 - Quantum Field Theory Redux/Essays on Modern Times, 1960-1983, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 21 - Essays on Modern Times, 1960-1983, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 22 - Being a Conclusion that Begins [Starts] as Epilog and Ends as Prolog, undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Publication - Post-I.B. ["Inward Bound"], [1931-1961], 1986-1988 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Publication - Book 2, 1980-1984 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Publication - "Inward Bound", [1897-1978], 1981-1989; Folder 1 or 2 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Publication - "Inward Bound", [1897-1978], 1981-1989; Folder 2 or 2 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Publication - I.B. ["Inward Bound"] Errata, 1986-1988 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - "A Tale of Two Continents", 1942-1998; 5
    The materials for this book are broken down in order of the publication process, beginning with Reference notes that include material collected on the subject matter such as handwritten notes, newspaper and journal articles, as well as copies of book chapters and other related archival material depending on the subject. This is followed by the Manuscripts which include both handwritten and typed drafts of chapters of the different books. The last section is Publication and this includes primary correspondence with the publishers, edits to the book, copies of the book covers and reviews of the books.
    Of special note in this subseries is a folder of original Dutch newspapers from 1945 to the immediate post-war period. Archival copies have been made, and the originals have been moved into a separate box at the end of the collection.
    - Reference Notes, 1942, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Newspapers, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - War, 1947-1992 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Postwar, 1945-1993 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 1-10, undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 1-11, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 11-14, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 15-22, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 15-22, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 23-28, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 23-28, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 29-33, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Chapters 29-33, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Publication - A Tale of Two Continents, 1997-1998 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Originals - Reference Notes - Newspapers, 1945 (Box 93, Folder 1)
  - Essays, Articles and Unpublished Manuscripts, 1859-2001; 6
    The materials in this subseries are arranged alphabetically.
    This subseries consists of essays, articles and unpublished manuscripts.
    - "American Scientist" - "How Einstein Got the Nobel Prize", July/August 1982 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Anti-neutrino Reactions, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Approximate Unitary Symmetry and the Parity Question, 1964 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Born, Max, 1926-1982 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Classical Example of Essentially Singular Coupling, 1964 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Comments on the Present Status of the Strong Interactions Problems - Unpublished Manuscript, undated (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Compton Scattering on Stable Targets of Arbitrary Spin, undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - CP-Invariance & 2pi-Modes of Long-Lived Neutral K-Particles (Pais/Grsey), undated (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Dirac, 1947-1999 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - The Discovery of the Electron, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - The Dynamics of Science, 1921-1986 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - The Dynamics of Science, 1955-1998 (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Energy Bounds for Charm and for Heavy Lepton Production in the e+ e- Annihilation, 1974-1977 (Box 24, Folder 16)
    - Energy Peaks, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Einstein Addenda, 1910-1990; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Einstein Addenda, 1910-1990; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - A.E. [Albert Einstein] - A. A. A. S. [American Association for the Advancement of Science] Lecture, 1980 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Einstein Manuscripts, 1981-1982 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Einstein: Origin of E. Legend, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Fermilab Paper, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - A Field Theory of Weak Interactions I, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - A Field Theory of Weak Interactions I, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - A Field Theory of Weak Interactions II, undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Freeman Dyson, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Glimpses of Oskar Klein as Scientist and Thinker, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - The Image of Physics - Unpublished Manuscript, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - On a Plane Ising Lattice with First and Second Interactions, 1941-1963 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - "Journal of Jocular Physics" - Vol. I-III, 1945-1955 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - "Journal on Nuclear Eqs.", 1951; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - "Journal on Nuclear Eqs.", 1951; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Lorentz Invariance & SU(6) Theory (Pais with Beg), 1965 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Lorentz Invariance & SU(6) Theory II (Pais with Beg), undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - The Many pi-Meson Problem II, undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Marie Curie, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-2001 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Quote Sources, 1944-1993 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Niels Bohr on the Danish Scene, undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Nuclear Physics in the Netherlands, the Early Years, 1990 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Notes on W3, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Parity SU(6), undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - "Particle Jungle" (TV Manuscript), 1965 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Particles, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Paul Dirac: Aspects of His Life and Work, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Peaks in Mesonic Systems (Nauenberg/Pais), 1964 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Pauli, Wolfgang, 1955, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Phase Shift Extraction...., undated (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - "The Physical Review:" Then and Now, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Physics in Denmark, from a College for the Clergy to Modern Times, 1996 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - "Physics Today" [Pais article, "The Princeton Period"], 1967 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - "Physics Today" [Pais contribution, "Stalin, Fuchs, and the Soviet Bomb"], 1990 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - pi lamda - Phase Shift Information...., undated (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Pion Phase-Shift Information from K [subscript 14] Decays, 1968 and other (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Planck, Max (Materials for Essays), undated (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Planck, Max, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Polaron, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - The Power of the Word, undated (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Problems in the Theory of Elementary Particles, undated (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Quadruple Moment, undated (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Reflections on Bohr and Einstein, undated (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Relativistic Crossing Symmetric SU(6), undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Reminiscences from the Post-War Years, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Res Jost, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Reviews and Articles, 1958-1986 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Scattering Formalism for Singular Potential Theory, undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Shabbos in Cecilienhof, undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Siena, "Methods and Problems in the Dynamics of Weak Interactions", undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Singular Potentials and Peratization II (Pais/Wu), undated (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Spin, 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Spin - Unitary Spin Independence (Pais), undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Spin - Unitary Spin Independence II, undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Spin, Unitary Spin and Weak Interactions (Unpublished Manuscript), undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Spin/Weak Interactions, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - [A Study of K Decay], undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - SU(6) Completed, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - SU(6) - Old Notes, 1964-1965 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - SU(6)/Semi-leptonic Interactions (Pais/Beg), 1964 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - A Suggestion Concerning the Reflexion Properties of Hyperons and K-Meson (Unpublished Manuscript), undated (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Review of "Symmetries and Reflections" and Article; "Low Energy Theorems for Spin....", undated (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Theoretical High Energy Physics, undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Theoretical Particle Physics, 1999 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Tops - "Excursion into the Theory of Tops", undated (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Uhlenbeck, G. E., 1859-1990; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Uhlenbeck, G. E., 1859-1990; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Uhlenbeck, G. E., 1916-1989; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Uhlenbeck, G. E., 1916-1989; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Uhlenbeck, G. E. - Heraldries, 1982 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Untitled, Unpublished Manuscript, undated (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Vector Meson Theory, 1950-1964 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Vector Model, 1952 and undated drafts (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Vertices with Partial SU(6,6) Structure, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Victor Friedrich Weisskopf, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Weak Interactions I, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Weak Interactions II, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Weak Interactions III, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Weak Interactions - "A Field Theory of Weak Interactions III" [Unpublished], undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Woolly Cusp (Galley Proof), undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Yang-Mills, 1953-1983 (Box 31, Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1895-1999; 3; 5.4 Cubic Feet
  This series contains primarily material collected on various subjects such as unified field theory, statistical physics and quantum theory. This includes copies of articles, newspaper clippings, some correspondence and some archival material from other collections. Some of this material was most likely used as a reference source for various articles and essays published by Pais. This series also contains conference-related material such as the Kyoto International Symposium in 1985 and the Conference on Ludwig Boltzmann in 1983. There are also some biographical materials on various physicists including Freeman Dyson, Richard Feynman and C. N. Yang. Additionally, there are faculty and personal materials from the Institute for Advanced Study, Rockefeller University and Pais' 70th birthday celebration at the Rockefeller University.
  - A (Abraham - "Art Quarterly"), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - A (Alembic Club - Andrade), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Abraham Pais - "Current Biography", 1994 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Accelerators, 1948-1986 (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - A.I.P. [American Institute of Physics], 1974-1976 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - [American Focus Lecture] (Poster), 1995 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Appendices, 1923-1980 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1968, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Astrophysics, 1978 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - [Atomic Energy Bills], [1945, 1973-1982] (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - B (Baheall - Brown), undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - B (Badash - Boltzmann), undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - B (Born - Bush), undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - B-decay, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Bohr, Niels [Commemoration of 50th Anniversary of First Papers], 1963 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - de Broglie, Louis, (1922-1925, 1962-1989) (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - C (Casimir - Cohen), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - C (Casimir - Curie), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology - Aubrey Butler Mickelwait, undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Chaos I, (1883)-1992 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Chaos II, (1927)-1992 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Charm, 1976 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Collaborators, 1920-1984 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Condensation, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Conference on Ludwig Boltzmann, 1981 & 1983 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Cosmic Rays, (1911)-1981 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - CP-violation, 1955-1970; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - CP-violation, 1975-1989; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Cusps, undated (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - D (Dllenbach - Douglas), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - D (Danysz - Duhem), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Deuterium CS, 1960-1961 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Dispersion Relations (by Michael Nauenberg), 1961 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Dyson, Freeman, (1980, 1996) (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - E (Earman - Epstein), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - E (Earnshaw - Erds), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - ETH [Eidg. Technischen Hochschule], (1905)-1981 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Experimental Nuclear Physics, 1932-1987 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - F (Faraday - Freundlich), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - F (Farrar - Freundenthal), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Faust - Eine Historie, 1932 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Feigenbaum & Libchaber, 1979-1991; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Feigenbaum & Libchaber, 1980, 1986-1990; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Feigenbaum Papers, 1976-1994 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Feynman, Richard P., January-March 1951 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Feynman, Richard P., 1986-1991 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Fretter & Leighton, V-Particle Pictures, undated (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Freudenthal, 1959-1961 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - G (Garnow - Guth), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - G (Gilbert - Gyldn), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - Gell-Mann/K-K, 1953-1989 (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - GR [General Relativity], 1975-1985 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - H (Habicht - Hilbert), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - H (Hoff - Hubble), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - H (Hadamard - Henry), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - H (Hermann - Hund), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Haas Effect, 1918-1935, 1970-1982 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Heisenberg, Werner, 1930-1939, 1950-1953 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Hermann, A., undated (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Herring, C., undated (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - History of Physics, 1904-1976 [with gaps] (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Holland (maps), undated (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - I-J (Infeld - Jeans), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - I-J (Infeld - Jeffery), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Institute for Advanced Study, 1936-1981 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Institute for Advanced Study, 1947-1960 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Institute for Advanced Study, 1956, 1973-1974 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Institutions, 1910-1992; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Institutions, 1910-1992; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Jost, Professor R., 1926-1977, 1984-1997 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - K (Kac - Kronig), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - K (Klein - Kronig), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Klein, M., 1959-1982 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Kos, undated (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Kramers, H., 1952-1983, 1991-1996 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - L (Lampa - Lense), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - L (Le Verrier - Lorentz), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Laboratories, 1953, 1977-1987 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Lnczos, Cornelius, 1974-1975 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - LET [Linear Energy Transfer], undated (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - The Lewis Thomas Prize, 1995, 1999 (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Lorentz Correspondence, [(1906)-1960] (Box 40, Folder 9)
    Contains undated notes by Abraham Pais.
  - M (Mach - Mehra), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - M (Melcher - Miller), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - M (Mach - Mehra), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - M (Meritt - Mulliken), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - McCormmach, Russell, 1966, 1969, 1974 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Meson50 - Kyoto International Symposium: The Jubilee of the Meson Theory [Envelope], 1985 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Monopoles, 1977, 1981-1984 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - N (Nobel - Nordstrm), undated (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - N-O (Nagaoka - Oort), undated (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Nernst, (1898-1918) (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - New Physics, 1968-1985; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - New Physics, 1982-1998; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, 1919-1920, 1933, 1955, 1979 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Niels Bohr Foundation, 1933-1987; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Niels Bohr Foundation, 1933-1987; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Niels Bohr - War, 1936-1962, 1984-1990; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Niels Bohr - War, 1943-1980; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Nobel Prizes, 1900-1935; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Nobel Prizes, 1960-1984; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Old Quantum Theory, 1903-1987; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Old Quantum Theory, 1903-1987; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Old Quantum Theory, 1903-1987; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - P (Pauli - Photoelectric Effect), undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - P (Placzek - Poincar), undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - P (Pringsheim - Pyenson), undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Particles & Field, 1931-1932, 1962-1977 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Pauli, Franca, 1959-1986 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Pauli, W., 1930-1958, 1976-1992; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Pauli, W., 1933-1994; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Perihelion, 1903, 1922 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Photoeffect, 1912-1916 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Physics in the Netherlands, 1931-1960, 1990 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Physiology, 1896-1936, 1962, 1973 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Physiology-Ra, 1900-1952, 1975-1983 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Portugal (maps), undated (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1958 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Publications - College Life, 1968 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Quantum Mechanics, 1930, 1954, 1975-1989 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - R (Rabi - Rydberg), undated (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Rabi, I. I., 1946, 1970-1996; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Rabi, I. I., 1946, 1970-1996; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Reference Notes, undated (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Reviews, 1986-1999 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller Institute, 1967-1996 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    Restricted from scholarly research.
  - Russian for the Scientist, undated (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Rutherford, Ernest, 1903-1913, 1968, 1991 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - S (Salaman - Sutherland), undated (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - S (Sagnac - Silliman), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - S (Smyth - Stuewer), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Scattering Cusps, undated (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - Scattering Theory, undated (Box 46, Folder 10)
  - Schulmann, Robert - Note, undated (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Schweber, Silvan, 1928, 1989 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - "Serber Says", 1947 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - 70th Birthday, 1988 (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - SF- - Dr. E [Einstein], 1917-1920, 1981 (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Smoluchowski - Opalescence, 1908-1957 (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Speiser, D., 1984 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Spin, 1922-1930, 1953-1982; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Spin, 1922-1930, 1953-1982; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Stachel, John, 1971-1983 (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - Statistical Physics, (1865)-1895, 1957-1981; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Statistical Physics, (1865)-1895, 1957-1981; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Students, 1981-1982 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - T (Talmey - Treder), undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - T (Tait - Tuan), undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Tashkent, 1972 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Theoretical Nuclear Physics, 1936-1988; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Theoretical Nuclear Physics, 1936-1988; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - U (Uehling - Urey), undated (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - UFT [Unified Field Theory], 1918-1979; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 48, Folder 10)
  - UFT [Unified Field Theory], 1918-1979; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Uhlenbeck, 1963-1979 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - U, V, W (Unsld - Winteler), undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - V (van der Wrden - Verwey), undated (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Varia, 1927-1990 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Varia - Amsterdam, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Varia - Family/Parents, 1956-1969, n.d. (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Velocity of Light, 1964 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - W (van der Waals - Wooster), undated (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - Weak Interactions I & II, undated (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Wigner, Eugene P., 1926-1998; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Wigner, Eugene P., 1926-1998; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Wu, C. S., 1952-1977 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Y, Z (Young - Zernike), undated (Box 50, Folder 2)